<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sample>

  <name>jasper</name>
  <title>Jasper Sample</title>
  <description>Shows how different features of the library could be used to generate a complex document.</description>

  <mainFeature ref="groups"/>
  <mainFeature ref="csvmetadataexport"/>
  <mainFeature ref="conditionalstyles"/>
  
  <!-- groups -->
  
  <feature name="groups" title="Data Grouping">
    <description>
How to group data at different levels and perform aggregate calculations using report groups.
    </description>
    <since>0.1.0</since>
    <documentedBy>
      <author>
    	<name>Sanda Zaharia</name>
    	<email>shertage@users.sourceforge.net</email>
      </author>
    </documentedBy>
  	<otherSample ref="datasource"/>
    <content>
<subtitle name="grouping_overview">Grouping Data in JasperReports</subtitle>
<br/>
<br/>
A report's content can be better organized if the report data are grouped by meaningful criteria. For instance, 
a shipping report becomes more relevant when its data are grouped by product type, or by customer's country, etc. 
<br/>
And as a bonus, grouped data allow statistic calculations to be performed and additional statistic information 
to be added to the report at runtime.
<br/>
As seen above, there are multiple reasons of grouping and aggregating data before they are represented. In JasperReports 
there are two ways to accomplish this:
<ul>
<li>If a report query is declared, it could be customized to retrieve already aggregated data from the data source 
(A SQL query could use the <code>GROUP BY</code> clause and statistical functions, for example). The main advantage 
is that the JR engine needs no more to prepare data before representing it, and the report is running faster in this 
case. The main disadvantage is that one cannot use the group imbrication, along with group header and footer facilities, 
so the data presentation can be realized in simplified layouts only.</li>
<li>If a rich presentation context of data grouping is required, one could use the report <code>&lt;group/&gt;</code> 
elements. Groups represent a flexible way to organize data on a report. In this case, the engine iterates through 
records in the data source and retrieves only those according to the grouping criteria.</li>
</ul>
A report group has three components: 
<ul>
<li>Group expression - contains the data grouping criteria. When the value of the group expression 
changes during the iteration through the data source at report-filling time, a group rupture occurs 
and the corresponding &lt;groupFooter&gt; and &lt;groupHeader&gt; sections are inserted into the 
resulting document.</li>
<li>Group header section - a multiband section containing header additional information.</li>
<li>Group footer section - a multiband section containing footer additional information.</li>
</ul>
<b>Note</b>:
<ul>
<li>The order of groups declared in a report template is important because groups contain each other. 
One group contains the following group, and so on. When a larger group encounters a rupture, all 
subsequent groups are reinitialized.</li>
<li>You can declare as many groups as you want in a report.</li>
<li>In order to get an accurate data representation, the data in the data source should be 
already ordered according to the group expressions used in the report. One can either perform data 
sorting through the report query, or use the <code>&lt;sortField/&gt;</code> element.</li>
</ul>
<subtitle name="attributes">Group Attributes</subtitle>
<br/>
<br/>
Any group in a report can be customized through its attributes:
<ul>
<li><code>name</code> - Acts as a group identifier. This attribute is mandatory, and should be unique per report.</li>
<li><code>isStartNewColumn</code> - Instructs the engine to start a new column when a new group starts. The default 
value is <code>false</code>.</li>
<li><code>isStartNewPage</code> - Instructs the engine to start a new page when a new group starts. The default 
value is <code>false</code>.</li>
<li><code>isResetPageNumber</code> - If <code>true</code>, when a new group starts, the built-in <code>PAGE_NUMBER</code> 
variable will be reset. The default value is <code>false</code>.</li>
<li><code>isReprintHeaderOnEachPage</code> - Instructs the engine to print the group header on each page containing 
the group data. The default value is <code>false</code>.</li>
<li><code>minHeightToStartNewPage</code> - Represents the minimum amount of vertical space at 
the bottom of the page or column, measured in pixels, that prevents the group from starting a 
new page of its own.</li>
<li><code>footerPosition</code> - Specifies the rendering position of the group footer on the page. Possible values are: 
<code>Normal</code>, <code>StackAtBottom</code>, <code>ForceAtBottom</code>, <code>CollateAtBottom</code>. 
The default value is <code>Normal</code>.</li>
<li><code>keepTogether</code> - If <code>true</code>, prevents the group from splitting on its first break attempt. 
The default value is <code>false</code>.</li>
</ul>
<subtitle name="variables">Data Grouping and Report Variables</subtitle>
<br/>
<br/>
Report variables are special objects built on top of a report expression in order to apply the code 
reusability during the report design stage. Report templates are a lot simplified when expressions 
frequently used throughout the report template are declared in a single place as objects that can 
be referenced by their name as unique identifier.
<br/>
Another great advantage of declaring expressions as variables is the ability to perform various 
calculations based on their corresponding expression. 
<br/>
A report variable is characterized by the following attributes:
<ul>
<li><code>name</code> - The variable's name used as unique identifier. It is mandatory.</li>
<li><code>class</code> - The class name of the variable's values. The default class is <code>java.lang.String</code></li>
<li><code>resetType</code> - Indicates when the variable should be reinitialized during the report-filling process. Possible 
values are:<code>None</code>, <code>Report</code>, <code>Page</code>, <code>Column</code>, <code>Group</code>. The default 
value is <code>Report</code>.</li>
<li><code>resetGroup</code> - If the <code>resetType</code> is set to <code>Group</code>, indicates the name of the group 
which triggers the variable reinitializing each time it breaks.</li>
<li><code>incrementType</code> - Indicates when the variable should be incremented during the report-filling process. Possible 
values are:<code>None</code>, <code>Report</code>, <code>Page</code>, <code>Column</code>, <code>Group</code>. The default 
value is <code>None</code>.</li>
<li><code>incrementGroup</code> - If the <code>incrementType</code> is set to <code>Group</code>, indicates the name of the group 
which triggers the variable increment each time it breaks.</li>
<li><code>calculation</code> - Indicates the built-in calculation type to be performed on the variable expression value. Possible 
values are:<code>Nothing</code>, <code>Count</code>, <code>DistinctCount</code>, <code>Sum</code>, <code>Average</code>, <code>Lowest</code>, 
<code>Highest</code>, <code>StandardDeviation</code>, <code>Variance</code>, <code>System</code>, <code>First</code>. The default 
value is <code>Nothing</code>.</li>
<li><code>incrementerFactoryClass</code> - The name of the incrementer factory class.</li>
</ul>
<b>Note</b>: With every iteration through the data source, variables are evaluated/incremented in the same order as they are 
declared. Therefore, the order of variables as they appear in the report template is very important. 
<br/>
For more about report variables one can consult also the 
<a href="http://jasperforge.org/uploads/publish/jasperreportswebsite/trunk/tutorial.html#Variables">tutorial</a>.
<br/>
<br/>
Being familiarized with variables, it's time to focus back on data grouping. Report variables are very useful objects in a report, 
that can operate on any collection of data. Since groups are aggregating data in meaningful collections, variables could be used 
to perform operations at group level too. As seen above, they can be reset or incremented any time a group breaks, and can be used 
to perform various built-in calculations over parameters, other variables and/or field values in a group.
<br/>
Related to groups, there is a special built-in counting variable, used to count the number of records in a group. This type of variables 
are always named with the related group's name followed by the <code>_COUNT</code> suffix. In this sample we'll find some usage examples 
of this group counting variables. 
<br/>
<br/>
<subtitle name="jasper_sample">The Jasper Sample</subtitle>
<br/>
<br/>
This sample illustrates how groups can be used to produce documents with complex data grouping in a 
multicolumn layout. The <code>reports/FirstJasper.jrxml</code> file describes a shipping report presented 
in a 2-column layout, with data organized according to several specific grouping criteria. 
<br/>
The 2-column layout is given by the <code>columnCount="2"</code> attribute setting in the 
<code>&lt;jasperReport/&gt;</code> element.
<br/>
<br/>
Further, one can see the report query retrieving data ordered by the <code>ShipCountry</code> field: 
<pre><![CDATA[
  <queryString><![CDATA[SELECT * FROM Orders WHERE OrderID <= $P{MaxOrderID} ORDER BY ShipCountry]] ></queryString>]]></pre>
Next in the report are defined some variables related to groups:
<pre><![CDATA[
  <variable name="FirstLetter" class="java.lang.String" resetType="None">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{ShipCountry}.substring(0, 1).toUpperCase()]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>
  <variable name="FreightSumFirstLetterGroup" class="java.lang.Double" resetType="Group" 
    resetGroup="FirstLetterGroup" calculation="Sum">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{Freight}]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>
  <variable name="FreightSumCountryGroup" class="java.lang.Double" resetType="Group" 
    resetGroup="CountryGroup" calculation="Sum">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{Freight}]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>
  <variable name="FreightSumColumn" class="java.lang.Double" resetType="Column" calculation="Sum">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{Freight}]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>
  <variable name="FreightSumPage" class="java.lang.Double" resetType="Page" calculation="Sum">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{Freight}]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>
  <variable name="FreightSumReport" class="java.lang.Double" calculation="Sum">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{Freight}]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>
  <variable name="DateHighestCountryGroup" class="java.sql.Timestamp" resetType="Group" 
    resetGroup="CountryGroup" calculation="Highest">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{OrderDate}]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>
  <variable name="RegionCountCountryGroup" class="java.lang.Integer" resetType="Group" 
    resetGroup="CountryGroup" calculation="Count">
    <variableExpression><![CDATA[$F{ShipRegion}]] ></variableExpression>
  </variable>]]></pre>
Now let's take a look at the groups themselves:
<pre><![CDATA[
<group name="FirstLetterGroup" isStartNewColumn="true" isReprintHeaderOnEachPage="true" 
  minHeightToStartNewPage="200">
  <groupExpression><![CDATA[$V{FirstLetter}]] ></groupExpression>
  <groupHeader>
    <band height="25">
      ...
      <textField>
        <reportElement mode="Opaque" x="130" y="14" width="140" height="11" forecolor="#ff0000" 
          backcolor="#ffdddd" style="Sans_Bold"/>
        <textFieldExpression class="java.lang.String"><![CDATA[$V{FirstLetter}]] ></textFieldExpression>
      </textField>
    </band>
  </groupHeader>
  <groupFooter>
    <band height="15">
      ...
      <textField>
        <reportElement x="45" y="1" width="25" height="11" forecolor="#ff0000" style="Sans_Bold"/>
        <textElement textAlignment="Right"/>
        <textFieldExpression class="java.lang.Integer"><![CDATA[$V{FirstLetterGroup_COUNT}]] ></textFieldExpression>
      </textField>
      ...
      <textField pattern="0.00">
        <reportElement x="170" y="1" width="60" height="11" forecolor="#ff0000" style="Sans_Bold"/>
        <textElement textAlignment="Right"/>
        <textFieldExpression class="java.lang.Double"><![CDATA[$V{FreightSumFirstLetterGroup}]] ></textFieldExpression>
      </textField>
      <textField evaluationTime="Auto">
        <reportElement x="230" y="1" width="40" height="11" forecolor="#ff0000" style="Sans_Bold"/>
        <textElement textAlignment="Right"/>
        <textFieldExpression>
          <![CDATA[
            msg("{0,number,0.00}%", 
            new Double(100d * $V{FreightSumFirstLetterGroup}.doubleValue() / $V{FreightSumReport}.doubleValue()))
          ]] >
        </textFieldExpression>
      </textField>
    </band>
  </groupFooter>
</group>]]></pre>
According to the group expression above, the <code>FirstLetterGroup</code> groups data with the same 
first letter of the <code>ShipCountry</code> field. All countries starting with the same letter 
will be grouped together. When the first letter changes, the <code>FirstLetterGroup</code> group 
will break.
<br/>
One can see also, from attribute settings, that this group will start in a new column, each time 
printing its header too, and requires a minimum 200px amount of vertical space in order to prevent 
starting on a new page by its own.
<br/>
Another interesting element here is the built-in variable <code>FirstLetterGroup_COUNT</code> which 
counts the number of records in the group. One could notice the variable's name consisting in the 
related group's name followed by the <code>_COUNT</code> suffix.
<br/>
Other report variables, such as <code>FreightSumFirstLetterGroup</code> and <code>FreightSumReport</code> 
were used too, in order to perform statistic calculations.
<br/>
<br/>
Now let's jump to the next group in the report. The <code>FirstLetterGroup</code> group contains records 
for all countries starting with the same letter. It means that for groups containing more than one country, records 
for different countries are mixed together, and this might be not a very good idea. Obviously, a better data grouping 
procedure is required. For instance, to create a child group inside the <code>FirstLetterGroup</code> for each distinct 
country starting with that letter. So, the information will become more readable and significant than before.
<br/>
This is what the second group in the report does, the <code>CountryGroup</code>: 
<pre><![CDATA[
<group name="CountryGroup" isReprintHeaderOnEachPage="true">
  <groupExpression><![CDATA[$F{ShipCountry}]] ></groupExpression>
  <groupHeader>
  <band height="15">
    ...
    <textField evaluationTime="Group" evaluationGroup="CountryGroup" pattern="EEE, MMM d, yyyy">
      <reportElement x="170" y="2" width="100" height="11" style="Sans_Bold"/>
      <textElement textAlignment="Right"/>
      <textFieldExpression class="java.sql.Timestamp"><![CDATA[$V{DateHighestCountryGroup}]] ></textFieldExpression>
    </textField>
  </band>
  </groupHeader>
  <groupFooter>
  <band height="15">
    ...
    <textField>
      <reportElement mode="Opaque" x="45" y="0" width="25" height="11" backcolor="#c0c0c0" style="Sans_Bold"/>
      <textElement textAlignment="Right"/>
      <textFieldExpression class="java.lang.Integer"><![CDATA[$V{CountryGroup_COUNT}]] ></textFieldExpression>
    </textField>
    ...
    <textField pattern="0.00">
      <reportElement mode="Opaque" x="170" y="0" width="60" height="11" backcolor="#c0c0c0" style="Sans_Bold"/>
      <textElement textAlignment="Right"/>
      <textFieldExpression class="java.lang.Double"><![CDATA[$V{FreightSumCountryGroup}]] ></textFieldExpression>
    </textField>
    <textField evaluationTime="Auto">
      <reportElement mode="Opaque" x="230" y="0" width="40" height="11" backcolor="#c0c0c0" style="Sans_Bold"/>
      <textElement textAlignment="Right"/>
      <textFieldExpression><![CDATA[msg("{0,number,0.00}%", new Double(100d * $V{FreightSumCountryGroup}.doubleValue() / $V{FreightSumFirstLetterGroup}.doubleValue()))]] ></textFieldExpression>
    </textField>
  </band>
  </groupFooter>
</group>
]]></pre>
Here one can observe another built-in counting variable: <code>CountryGroup_COUNT</code>. Again some other report variables 
are used to perform various calculations: <code>DateHighestCountryGroup</code>, <code>FreightSumCountryGroup</code>, 
<code>FreightSumFirstLetterGroup</code>. The group header will also be reprinted on each new page.
<br/>
<br/>
At this stage we can represent data in a user-friendly form, well separated by countries and country first letters, in a 
2-columns layout. What else could be done to separate data better than that?
<br/>
Well, there is one more thing. What if for a given country there are thousands of records? One after one, after one, and so 
on. Thousands of records looking the same, with nothing special to separate them, increasing a lot the eye's effort... It 
doesn't sound very good, indeed.
<br/>
This is why the third group in the report is present. It is an empty dummy group that breaks after every 5 records, introducing 
a supplementary amount of vertical space between the resulting 5-records groups:
<pre><![CDATA[
  <group name="BreakGroup">
    <groupExpression><![CDATA[new Boolean($V{BreakGroup_COUNT}.intValue() > 5)]] ></groupExpression>
    <groupHeader>
    <band height="5">
    </band>
    </groupHeader>
    <groupFooter>
    <band height="5">
    </band>
    </groupFooter>
  </group>]]></pre>
Once finished the data grouping work, the report template continues with its usual sections, such as <code>title</code>, 
<code>title</code>, <code>pageHeader</code>, <code>columnHeader</code>, <code>detail</code>, <code>columnFooter</code>, 
<code>pageFooter</code> and <code>summary</code>.
<br/>
At this moment the sample is ready to be ran.
<br/>
<br/>
<subtitle name="running_sample">Running the Sample</subtitle>
<br/>
<br/>
Running the sample requires the <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">Apache Ant</a> library. Make sure that <code>ant</code> is already installed on your system (version 1.5 or later).
<br/>
In a command prompt/terminal window set the current folder to <code>demo/hsqldb</code> within the JasperReports source project and run the <code>&gt; ant runServer</code> command. 
It will start the HSQLDB server shipped with the JasperReports distribution package. Let this terminal running the HSQLDB server.  
<br/>
Open a new command prompt/terminal window and set the current folder to <code>demo/samples/jasper</code> within the JasperReports source project and run the <code>&gt; ant test view</code> command.
<br/>
It will generate all supported document types containing the sample report in the <code>demo/samples/jasper/build/reports</code> directory. 
<br/>
Then the report will open in the JasperReports internal viewer.

    </content>
  </feature>

  <!-- csvmetadataexport -->
  
  <feature name="csvmetadataexport" title="Exporting to CSV Format Using Report Metadata">
    <description>
Shows how to export the report to CSV format using metadata associated with report elements at design time, to mark data columns.
    </description>
    <since>4.0.0</since>
    <documentedBy>
      <author>
    	<name></name>
    	<email></email>
      </author>
    </documentedBy>
    <content>
[Under Construction]
    </content>
  </feature>

  <!-- conditionalstyles -->
  
  <feature name="conditionalstyles" title="Conditional Styles">
    <description>
Shows how to define and use a conditional style in a report template.
    </description>
    <since>1.2.0</since>
    <documentedBy>
      <author>
    	<name>Sanda Zaharia</name>
    	<email>shertage@users.sourceforge.net</email>
      </author>
    </documentedBy>
  	<otherSample ref="scriptlet"/>
  	<otherSample ref="crosstabs"/>
  	<otherSample ref="list"/>
    <content>
<subtitle  name="styles_overview">Conditional Styles</subtitle>
<br/>
<br/>
In JasperReports styles are the bricks used to generate the report elements appearance. 
Styles mean anything about fonts, but also mean borders, horizontal and vertical alignment, 
element transparency or opacity, background and foreground colors, format patterns, text markup 
information, text rotation, and so on... Almost anything needed to set up a complex, 
elegant and meaningful element look and feel.
<br/>
However, there are situations when the L&amp;F depends on certain conditions determined only at runtime. 
The most common example is the necessity to use alternate row colors in a table with a large number 
of rows, in order to better distinguish between them. When the total number of rows is unknown at report 
design time, or if the row is used in the detail section, a tool for setting up different backgrounds 
for the same cell is definitely required.
<br/>
And here come conditional styles to get some help.
<br/>
<br/>
Conditional styles consist in two elements: a <code>Boolean</code> condition expression and a style. When the 
condition evaluates to <code>true</code>, the corresponding style is applied. In the 
<a href="#jasper">Jasper</a> sample one can see a conditional style definition:
<pre><![CDATA[
  <style name="Sans_Normal" isDefault="true" fontName="DejaVu Sans" fontSize="8" isBold="false" isItalic="false" isUnderline="false" isStrikeThrough="false"/>

  <style name="OrderIdStyle" style="Sans_Normal">
    <conditionalStyle>
      <conditionExpression><![CDATA[new Boolean($F{OrderID}.intValue() % 10 == 0)]] ></conditionExpression>
      <style forecolor="#ff0000" isBold="true"/>
    </conditionalStyle>
  </style>]]></pre>
The <code>OrderIdStyle</code> defined above derives from the <code>Sans_Normal</code> parent style. 
Usually, elements with <code>OrderIdStyle</code> will have the default black forecolor and a normal 
font weight. But when the condition expression evaluates to <code>true</code> (this happens each time  
the <code>OrderID</code> field value is a multiple of 10) the element's style changes: the forecolor 
becomes red and the font is displayed in bold style.
<br/>
Therefore, when applied, a conditional style will override the properties of its parent style. 
<br/>
<br/>
A style definition may contain many conditional styles, any of them inheriting from the parent style. 
In this case, all conditions that evaluate to <code>true</code> will append their own style properties 
to the existing style, in the same order they were defined in the report (the second style will be 
appended to the first one, and so on). If more than one conditional style affect the same style property, 
the property value will be done by the first conditional style in the styles sequence which evaluates its 
condition to <code>true</code>.
<br/>
Here is a more elaborate example:
<pre><![CDATA[
<style name="alternateStyle" fontName="Arial" forecolor="red">
  <conditionalStyle>
    <conditionExpression><![CDATA[new Boolean($V{REPORT_COUNT}.intValue() % 2 == 0)]] ></conditionExpression>
    <style forecolor="blue"/>
  </conditionalStyle>
  <conditionalStyle>
    <conditionExpression><![CDATA[new Boolean($F{AMOUNT}.intValue() > 10000)]] ></conditionExpression>
    <style isBold="true"/>
  </conditionalStyle>
  <conditionalStyle>
    <conditionExpression><![CDATA[new Boolean($F{AMOUNT}.intValue() > 20000)]] ></conditionExpression>
    <style isBold="false" isItalic="true"/>
  </conditionalStyle>
</style>]]></pre>
One can see above that on each even row the element forecolor becomes blue. More than that, if the <code>AMOUNT</code> 
field value is greater than 10,000, the second conditional style evaluates to <code>true</code>, and the element 
displays in bold font (this doesn't affect the red color or blue color set by the first conditional style, because the 
forecolor and font weight properties do not interfere). Further, if the <code>AMOUNT</code> field value is greater than 
20,000, the font style becomes italic, without affecting the font color. But because any value greater than 
20,000 is also greater than 10,000, then the <code>isBold="false"</code> font weight is no more applied, because 
both conditions <code>&gt;10,000</code> and <code>&gt;20,000</code> evaluate to <code>true</code> and <code>isBold="true"</code> 
style was appended first.
<br/>
<br/>
<b>Note:</b> 
<ul>
<li>By default, the style condition expressions are evaluated during the report filling at the moment they are actually used. 
The conditional expression evaluation is performed with the current values of referenced variables and fields in that moment, 
regardless of the evaluationTime attribute of the element itself.If the condition expression of the style needs a delayed evaluation, 
just like the value of the text field or the image element that uses the conditional style, the 
<code>net.sf.jasperreports.style.evaluation.time.enabled</code> configuration property should be set to <code>true</code>.</li>
<li>Conditional styles cannot be defined in style templates (see the <a href="../templates/index.html">Templates</a> sample). 
This is because style templates store styles with properties available for a large group of reports, while conditional styles 
are styles depending on conditions, variables and parameters specific to each report apart. However, styles defined in style 
templates can be used as parent styles for conditional styles.</li>
<li>Other examples of conditional styles can be found in <a href="../scriptlet/index.html">Scriptlet</a>, <a href="../list/index.html">List</a> and 
<a href="../crosstabs/index.html">Crosstabs</a> samples.</li>
</ul>
 </content>
  </feature>

</sample>
