<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<configReference>

  <category key="net.sf.jasperreports.metadata.property.category:chrome">
    <name>Chrome</name>
  </category>
  

  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.argument.{name} -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.argument.{name}">
    <description>
An arbitrary argument used when launching Chromium/Google Chrome.
<br/>
The {name} suffix is used as argument name, and the property value as
argument value.
A boolean property value is required for flags.
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.enabled -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.enabled">
    <description>
Determines whether Chromium/Google Chrome is to be used to render JavaScript based components
(such as Custom Visualization Components) for exporting to formats other than HTML.
<br/>
When enabled, a browser instance is launched (in headless mode by default) on the machine 
where JasperReports is running.
Scripts and resources needed to render the components are written to a temporary folder,
and JasperReports communicates with the browser instance via the Chrome DevTools Protocol.
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.executable.path -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.executable.path">
    <description>
The path of the Chromium/Google Chrome executable.
<br/>
If not set, a predefined list of common paths will be checked.
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.headless -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.headless">
    <description>
Determines whether Chromium/Google Chrome is to be launched in headless mode.
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.idle.timeout -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.idle.timeout">
    <description>
The number of milliseconds after which an idle Chromium/Google Chrome instance will be
shut down.
<br/>
After shuttind down an idle instnace, a fresh browser process is launched when needed.
<br/>
The property can be set to 0 to repress shutting down idle instances.
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.live.timeout -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.live.timeout">
    <description>
The number of milliseconds a Chromium/Google Chrome instance is allowed to live.
<br/>
The instance is shut down after the configured timeout, first waiting for the 
ongoing component render tasks to finish.
After shuttind down an instance, a fresh browser process is launched when needed.
<br/>
The property can be set to 0 to repress shutting down browser instances.
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.page.isolate -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.page.isolate">
    <description>
Whether to create Chrome pages in isolated mode for component render tasks.
<br/>
Isolated pages do not share cookies and other page data.
The implementation relies on the Chrome DevTools Protocol Target.createBrowserContext command.
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.page.timeout -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.page.timeout">
    <description>
The number of milliseconds after which a component render task is interrupted.
<br/>
A component render task usually consists of loading an HTML page from a temporary
file, running JavaScript code to render the component and retriving an SVG
representation of the component or taking a screenshot.
Interrupting a component render task raises an exception which in most cases
aborts the report export process.
<br/>
The property can be set to 0 to repress the interrupting component render tasks
(unless the component itself has a timeout defined).
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
  <!-- 	net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.tempdir.path -->
  
  <configProperty name="net.sf.jasperreports.chrome.tempdir.path">
    <description>
The path were temporary resource files used for rendering components will be written. 
    </description>
  </configProperty>
  
  
</configReference>
