<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sample>

  <name>javascript</name>
  <title>JavaScript Sample</title>
  <description>Shows how the JavaScript language could be used inside report templates.</description>

  <mainFeature ref="javascript"/>
  <secondaryFeature name="reportcompilers" sample="groovy" title="Report Compilers"/>
  
  <!-- javascript -->
  
  <feature name="javascript" title="Using the JavaScript Language for Report Expressions (JavaScript Report Compiler)">
    <description>
How to use JavaScript to write report expressions.
    </description>
    <since>3.1.2</since>
    <documentedBy>
      <author>
    	<name>Sanda Zaharia</name>
    	<email>shertage@users.sourceforge.net</email>
      </author>
    </documentedBy>
  	<otherSample ref="antcompile"/>
  	<otherSample ref="groovy"/>
  	<otherSample ref="java1.5"/>
    <content>
<b>JavaScript Scripting Example</b>
<br/>
<br/>
The main purpose of this sample is to show how the JavaScript compiler implementation works. Useful information 
about the default JavaScript compiler implementation can be found <a href="../groovy/index.html#jsCompiler">here</a>.
<br/>
This sample contains report expressions written using JavaScript. The 
<api href="net/sf/jasperreports/compilers/JavaScriptCompiler.html">JavaScriptCompiler</api> default implementation 
creates the JavaScript-related expression evaluator during the report compilation and prepares the <code>JasperReport</code> 
object for the filling process. 
<br/>
<br/>
In order to use JavaScript, the report <code>language</code> attribute is declared below: 
<br/>
<br/>
<code>language="javascript"</code>
<br/>
<br/>
In the report template are 
presented some JavaScript expressions which cannot be evaluated using Java, and one could notice some advantages 
that JavaScript scripting comes with.
<br/>
Having two numbers, 3 and 5, the report will output first their values as real numbers, and then their calculated sum. The two numbers 
are declared as follows:
<pre><![CDATA[
<parameter name="A" class="java.lang.Double">
  <defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[3]] ></defaultValueExpression>
</parameter>
<parameter name="B" class="java.lang.Double">
  <defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[5]] ></defaultValueExpression>
</parameter>]]></pre>
Both A and B values are declared of <code>java.lang.Double</code> type. But their values are let as primitive <code>int</code> types, because 
JavaScript is able to allocate types at runtime. All type conversions are performed dynamically, according to the type declarations above. 
The JavaScript scripting above uses a very simplified syntax. Taking into account the backward compatibility with JDK 1.4.x or earlier, 
equivalent Java expressions would be:
<pre><![CDATA[
<defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[Double.valueOf(3.0)]] ></defaultValueExpression>
<defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[Double.valueOf(5.0)]] ></defaultValueExpression>]]></pre>
The next two expressions in the report template read values from parameters declared above and store them in two text fields. 
These expressions can be evaluated using either JavaScript or Java:
<pre><![CDATA[
<expression><![CDATA[$P{A}]] ></expression>
...
<expression><![CDATA[$P{B}]] ></expression>]]></pre>
Next, the A + B sum is calculated within a JavaScript expression:
<pre><![CDATA[
<expression><![CDATA[Integer.valueOf($P{A} + $P{B})]] ></expression>]]></pre>
Object instantiation and type conversion are transparent processes here, the user only 
has to write a simple addition operation between the two report 
parameters (however, the specific parameter syntax still has to be respected). 
<br/>
The equivalent Java (1.4) expression would be:
<pre><![CDATA[
<expression><![CDATA[Double.valueOf($P{A}.doubleValue() + $P{B}.doubleValue())]] ></expression>]]></pre>
with a lot more complicated syntax.
<br/>
<br/>
<b>Running the Sample</b>
<br/>
<br/>
Running the sample requires the <a href="https://maven.apache.org/">Apache Maven</a> library. Make sure that <code>maven</code> is already installed on your system (version 3.6 or later).
<br/>
In a command prompt/terminal window set the current folder to <code>demo/samples/javascript</code> within the JasperReports source project 
and run the following command:
<br/>
<br/>
<code>&gt; mvn exec:java</code>
<br/>
<br/>
It will generate all supported document types containing the sample report in the <code>demo/samples/javascript/target/reports</code> directory.
    </content>
  </feature>

</sample>
