<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<sample>

  <name>java1.5</name>
  <title>Java 1.5 Sample</title>
  <description>Shows how Java 1.5 could be used inside report templates.</description>

  <mainFeature ref="java1.5"/>
  <secondaryFeature name="reportcompilers" sample="groovy" title="Report Compilers"/>
  
  <!-- java1.5 -->
  
  <feature name="java1.5" title="Using Java 1.5 Syntax in Report Expressions (Java 1.5 Report Compiler)">
    <description>
How to use Java 1.5 language specific features inside report expressions.
    </description>
    <since>1.1.1</since>
    <documentedBy>
      <author>
    	<name>Sanda Zaharia</name>
    	<email>shertage@users.sourceforge.net</email>
      </author>
    </documentedBy>
  	<otherSample ref="antcompile"/>
  	<otherSample ref="groovy"/>
  	<otherSample ref="javascript"/>
    <content>
<b>Java 1.5 Scripting Example</b>
<br/>
<br/>
The main purpose of this sample is to show how the Java 1.5 compiler implementation works. Useful information 
about various Java compiler implementations can be found <a href="../groovy/index.html#javaCompilers">here</a>.
<br/>
This sample contains report expressions written using Java 1.5. The 
<api href="net/sf/jasperreports/jdt/JRJdtCompiler.html">JRJdtCompiler</api> default implementation is Java 1.5-compatible and   
is strongly recommended to use it when handling Java 1.5-related expressions. 
<br/>
<br/>
In order to use Java 1.5, the report <code>language</code> attribute can be either not set (because Java represents the default scripting language), 
or declared as follows: 
<br/>
<br/>
<code>language="java"</code>
<br/>
<br/>
In the sample's report template the <code>language</code> attribute is not set.
<br/>
Next, one have to instruct the JDT compiler to observe Java 1.5 
code compatibility. In the /src/jasperreports.properties file the following properties are set:
<ul>
<li><code>org.eclipse.jdt.core.compiler.source=1.5</code></li>
<li><code>org.eclipse.jdt.core.compiler.compliance=1.5</code></li>
<li><code>org.eclipse.jdt.core.compiler.codegen.TargetPlatform=1.5</code></li>
</ul>
In the report template are included specific Java 1.5 expressions not compatible with Java 1.4 or earlier, requiring transparent 
autoboxing and unboxing, or enumerated types. An equivalent Java 1.4-compatible expression is also included, for comparison.
<br/>
Having two integer numbers, 3 and 5, the report will output first their values, and then their calculated sum. The two numbers 
are declared as follows:
<pre><![CDATA[
<parameter name="A" class="java.lang.Integer">
  <defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[3]] ></defaultValueExpression>
</parameter>
<parameter name="B" class="java.lang.Integer">
  <defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[5]] ></defaultValueExpression>
</parameter>]]></pre>
Both A and B values are declared of <code>java.lang.Integer</code> type. But their values are let as primitive <code>int</code> types, because 
Java 1.5 performs both autoboxing and unboxing mechanisms. When needed, primitive types are automatically converted into their wrapper class. 
The Java 1.5 syntax becomes a lot simplified. Equivalent Java 1.4 expressions would be:
<pre><![CDATA[
<defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[Integer.valueOf(3)]] ></defaultValueExpression>
<defaultValueExpression><![CDATA[Integer.valueOf(5)]] ></defaultValueExpression>]]></pre>
The next two expressions in the report template read values from parameters declared above and store them in two text fields. 
These expressions can be evaluated using either Java 1.5 or Java 1.4:
<pre><![CDATA[
<expression><![CDATA[$P{A}]] ></expression>
...
<expression><![CDATA[$P{B}]] ></expression>]]></pre>
Next, the A + B sum is calculated using a Java 1.4 expression:
<pre><![CDATA[
<expression><![CDATA[Integer.valueOf($P{A}.intValue() + $P{B}.intValue())]] ></expression>]]></pre>
A and B being <code>Integer</code>, their <code>intValue()</code> method is called in order to calculate the sum. 
After that, because the sum should be 
stored itself in an <code>Integer</code> value, an Integer object is made available for this purpose. The Java expression looks 
rather complicate and one has to take care to instantiate objects with their proper types in order to avoid class 
cast exceptions. 
<br/>
<br/>
Now, the same A + B sum is calculated using a Java 1.5 expression:
<pre><![CDATA[
<expression><![CDATA[Integer.valueOf($P{A} + $P{B})]] ></expression>]]></pre>
Object creation, autoboxing, unboxing and type conversion are transparent processes here, the user only 
has to write a simple addition operation between the two report 
parameters (however, the specific parameter syntax still has to be respected). 
<br/>
<br/>
Finally, depending on the <code>greeting</code> parameter's value, a greeting formula is shown. This parameter is an enumerated <code>Greeting</code> type 
(another specific Java 1.5 feature):
<pre><![CDATA[
<parameter name="greeting" class="Greeting"/>]]></pre>
The <code>Greeting</code> type is defined in the /src/Greeting.java file:
<pre><![CDATA[
public enum Greeting { bye, day }]]></pre>
When the parameter's value is <code>Greeting.bye</code>, the output message will be 'Bye!'; 
when the parameter's value is <code>Greeting.day</code>, the message will be 'Have a nice day!':
<pre><![CDATA[
<element kind="staticText" uuid="a35ba780-d85a-4740-aab3-6cb31954ad6a" y="450" width="480" height="35" horizontalTextAlign="Center" fontSize="24.0">
  <printWhenExpression><![CDATA[$P{greeting} == Greeting.bye]] ></printWhenExpression>
  <text><![CDATA[Bye!]] ></text>
</element>
<element kind="staticText" uuid="800911c7-c795-4589-9111-69d557cfea01" y="450" width="480" height="35" horizontalTextAlign="Center" fontSize="24.0">
  <printWhenExpression><![CDATA[$P{greeting} == Greeting.day]] ></printWhenExpression>
  <text><![CDATA[Have a nice day!]] ></text>
</element>]]></pre>
<b>Running the Sample</b>
<br/>
<br/>
Running the sample requires the <a href="https://maven.apache.org/">Apache Maven</a> library. Make sure that <code>maven</code> is already installed on your system (version 3.6 or later).
<br/>
In a command prompt/terminal window set the current folder to <code>demo/samples/java1.5</code> within the JasperReports source project 
and run the following command:
<br/>
<br/>
<code>&gt; mvn exec:java</code>
<br/>
<br/>
It will generate all supported document types containing the sample report in the <code>demo/samples/java1.5/target/reports</code> directory.
    </content>
  </feature>

</sample>
